We pick up on דף בכורות ז' עמוד א', Daf Bechorot Zayin
Amud Aleph, seven. We pick up on the very bottom of ו'
עמוד ב', Vav Amud Bet, and we are, where are we? We've
been talking about this very important principle which we're going to stay
on for today and for even I believe tomorrow, which is the
issue about things that come from non-kosher animals are non-kosher. Actually, no,
I think we, oh yeah, we are staying on it for a
few days. Non-kosher animals are non-kosher and kosher animals are kosher, and
we're starting by asking about the issue about, you know, about children
that look, the offsprings that look different, but also we've related also
to the issue of other products like milk, and the milk of
a camel is not kosher as well. So now the גמרא Gemara
picks it up from אלא מעתה, Ella Me'ata, one, two, three, seven
lines from the bottom. Line begins with the word מכיר, Machir, so
like four lines in. So the גמרא Gemara says, so one of
the ways we learned this out was the fact that the תורה
Torah repeated the word גמל. Gamal. It said גמל גמל Gamal Gamal
twice to tell you not only the camel not kosher, but even
the milk of a camel, or according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said that even if the offspring of a
cow looks like a camel, that's not kosher as well. So now
the גמרא Gemara is going to question the use of using the
double, the fact that it repeats it, right? It says it once
in ויקרא Vayikra and once in דברים. Devarim. The fact that it
repeats it, is that really the basis for דרשה? Drasha? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: אלא מעתה, Ella Me'ata, says the גמרא,
Gemara, if that's true, שפן שפן ארנבת ארנבת חזיר חזיר, Shafan Shafan,
Arnevet Arnevet, Chazir Chazir, להני הוא דאתו? Le'hanei Hu De'atu? How about
the fact that it repeats all of the animals, right? The rabbit
and the hare and the pig? So is it coming to tell
me this idea? I mean, you don't need it to say that
multiple times, whether it's about the issue of the milk or the
issue about, according to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, about an offspring of
a kosher animal that looks like a non-kosher one. So you don't
make those דרשות. Drashot. אלא לכדתניא, Ella Lechid'tanya,
why do we say in general that the whole thing was repeated
again in דברים Devarim once it said it in ויקרא? Vayikra? למה
נשנו בבהמה? Lama Nishnu Be'vehema? So why was it repeated by the
בהמות, Behemot, like by the mammals? מפני השסועה, Mipnei Ha'shasua,
because of the שסועה, Shasua, which the גמרא Gemara understands was a
type of a strange animal that had like a double back and
whatever. Anyway, and that that was another included in the non-kosher animals.
What? Yes. ובעופו, U've'ofo, why was the whole list of kosher, non-kosher
birds repeated, or non-kosher? מפני הראה, Mipnei Ha'ra'ah, because in one it
says דאה Da'ah and in one it says ראה Ra'ah to tell,
and the גמרא Gemara understands that those are different species, so therefore
it was repeated.
גמל גמל נמי להכי הוא דאתא. Gamal Gamal Nami Le'hachi Hu De'ata.
So when it repeats גמל, Gamal, it's not coming to tell you
this new thing, it's just because it's repeating the whole פרשה, Parsha,
and since it's repeating the whole פרשה, Parsha, it repeats all of
the specifics, but it's not coming to tell you these new laws.
Only one or two points is really why it's being repeated. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, כל היכא דאיכא למידרש דרשינן. Kol Heicha
De'ika Lemidrash Darshinan. If we can make a דרשה, Drasha, we'll make
a דרשה. Drasha. So if we have nothing to say, then we'll
say the whole thing was repeated to tell you one point. But
if we can have a way to explain why something was repeated,
we'd rather give it an explanation.
Okay, now let's move on. So you don't have to דרשן Darshan
the rest of it?
Well, if you can't דרשן Darshan it, it was all for the
other stuff. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now, back to, back to
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position. Again, we're sort of switching between the
question about an offspring of a kosher animal that looks non-kosher to
the question of a product of a non-kosher animal like milk and
so on. And actually today, thank you so much, actually today we
will be talking about bee's honey as well. But now we are
talking about the offspring. So let's take a look. תנו רבנן: Tanu
Rabbanan: רחל שילדה מין עז עז שילדה מין רחל פטור מן הבכורה.
Rachel She'yalda Min Ez, Ez She'yalda Min Rachel, Patur Min Ha'bechora. A
sheep that gives birth to something that looks like a goat, a
goat that gives birth to something that looks like a sheep, you're
exempt. Okay, that we've already said. ואם יש בו מקצת סימנים חייב.
Ve'im Yesh Bo Miktzat Simanim Chayav. However, if the offspring looks, has
some characteristics like the right trait, like the right species, like the
mother species, it's obligated. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon Omer, now this
issue about if it's the other species, if it looks like the
wrong species, is it obligated in בכורה? Bechora? Here רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon has a higher criteria. עד שיהיה ראשו ורובו דומה לאמו. Ad
She'yihiye Rosho Ve'rubo Domeh Le'imo. If it looks like a wrong species,
even if some of the traits are like the mother, you're still
exempt. You're only obligated if the head and the majority looks like
the mother. So meaning of the overall, meaning if some minor traits
are like a different species, not a problem, but the head, which
obviously is a much, very important defining identity, and the majority of
it, that looks, again, how exactly you define majority, halfway up the
length or, you know, that's not so clear, but the point is
it predominantly has to look like the mother. That's what he says
regarding the issue of בכורה, Bechora, a firstborn. But of course now
we're actually having our attention has shifted from firstborn to the question
of כשרות. Kashrut. And if you remember רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we've
been dealing with has a distinctive position by כשרות. Kashrut. He says
that if it looks like a non-kosher animal, that it's not kosher,
even if the mother was kosher. So now the question is how
much would it have to look like a kosher animal according to
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon to be kosher? Would he apply the same
standard he does by the issue of firstborn? So let's take the
look, let's take a look. He says, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
If the offspring of let's say a cow looks like a camel
and now you want it to be kosher according to Rabbi Shimon
because how it looks matters, does he need it to look the
majority like the mother or is it enough that it just has
some characteristics like the mother in order to be kosher? או לא?
O lo? By the issue of the מצוה Mitzvah firstborn it says
אך בכור שור. Ach bechor shor. You remember like two days ago
that was our דרשה. Drasha. However the firstborn of an ox, עד
שיהא שור ובכורו שור. Ad sheyei shor u'bechoro shor. Literally emphasized it
has to be the animal has to be a full ox just
like the mother just like the mother father whatever. Anyway it has
to be it has to be a full fully appear as that
מין. Min. And therefore you could understand Rabbi Shimon's demand that a
few characteristics are not enough. It has to majority the predominant look
like the right species. אבל לאכילה, Aval l'achilah, but when it comes
to eating, גמלו דאמר רחמנא. Gemalo d'amar Rachmana. It's the opposite. The
Torah emphasizes not that it has to look kosher but that if
it looks like a camel, גמלו דאמר רחמנא דאסיר. Gemalo d'amar Rachmana
d'asir. That's forbidden. האי שתיני מגמלו. Hai shtinei mi'gemalo. If it's not
fully like a camel, if the offspring of a cow has some
cow characteristics, שפיר דמי. Shapir dami. Maybe that would be okay. או
דילמא לא שנא? O dilma lo shna? Maybe it doesn't matter. Now
this by the way brings up a point that I'm always mentioning
which is it always matters which category you define and which one
is the everything else because obviously the everything else is often much
bigger than the category you're defining. So what the גמרא Gemara is
saying is like when it comes for בכור, Bechor, the category we
define it has to look like an ox, it has to look
like a sheep. So therefore you could say according to Rabbi Shimon
if having a few סימנים Simanim is not enough, it has to
predominantly look like an ox, predominantly look like a sheep. But by
non-kosher animals we're not defining what it has to look like to
be kosher, we're defining what it looks like to be not kosher.
If the offspring of a cow looks like a camel it's not
kosher. So therefore you could say even if it only had a
few characteristics that are cow-like, it's not fully like a camel, that
might suffice because there you don't have to look like a cow,
you just have to not look totally like a camel. So that's
the גמרא's Gemara question. Is it the same criteria or not? Or
here would we say a few characteristics is enough? So דף ז
עמוד א, Daf Zayin Amud Aleph, second line, תא שמע, Ta shema,
come and hear. בהמה טהורה שילדה מין בהמה טמאה. Behemah tehorah she'yaldah
min behemah temeiah. If a kosher animal gives birth to something of
a species of a non-kosher animal, that's what it looks, and Michael
keeps on asking like is this because of the father? We'll get
to the father actually today as well, last question. Right now we're
bracketing it, we're saying even assuming that mother and father are the
right species, for some reason the animal looks like of a different
species. Is that enough to change its הלכה? Halacha? So אסור באכילה.
Assur b'achilah. So this is obviously following the approach of Rabbi Shimon
and says yes, the way it looks is enough to determine its
status, it's forbidden to be eaten. ואם דומה ראשו ורובו לאמו, V'im
domeh rosho v'rubo l'imo, however if the head and the majority does
look like its mother, then חייב בבכורה, Chayav b'bechorah, then it's obligated
in the firstborn. Okay now of course we leapfrogged over the question
about what do you need for it to be permissible to be
eaten? We jumped right to the question of firstborn. So that is
the question: how do you read this ברייתא? Braisa? So first גמרא
Gemara assumes since it ignored it presumably it's the same law. So
when it says majority and head it's obligated in firstborn, presumably it
means also and that's what you need for it to be permissible
to be eaten. שמע מינה, Shma mina, from here you can infer
לאכילה נמי בעי רבי שמעון ראשו ורובו, L'achilah nami baye Rabbi Shimon
rosho v'rubo, that also to be permissible to be eaten the majority
and the head also have to look like the mother and it
cannot just be a few characteristics. So the גמרא Gemara says לא,
Lo, not necessarily. לבכורה דוקא, L'bechorah davka, maybe only for the status
of the firstborn, but to be kosher even some characteristics would have
been okay. דיקא נמי דקא שביק לאכילה וקא קמלי אבכורה. Deika nami
d'ka shavik l'achilah v'ka kamlei a'bechorah. Maybe actually that you could actually
infer that from the language because it skipped over, it ignored the
issue of eating and it went straight to the question of firstborn.
שמע מינה, Shma mina, so maybe from that we can infer לבכורה
הוא דבעי רבי שמעון ראשו ורובו. L'bechorah hu d'baye Rabbi Shimon rosho
v'rubo. Only for the issue of firstborn does it need the head
and the majority to look like the mother. אבל, Aval, okay Michael,
but ברייתא Braisa say the same thing it says other places as
well. Okay there's
no... no. אבל... Aval... אבל... Aval... it asks if it's obvious, it
doesn't ask if it was taught in another ברייתא. Braisa. A lot
of things are repeated. אבל לאכילה לא, Aval l'achilah lo, but presumably
since it went straight to the firstborn, presumably to be kosher for
eating even you don't need to go that far, even some סימנים
Simanim are okay. גמרא Gemara says לא. Lo. לעולם אימא לך, L'olam
eima lach, I could say to you לאכילה נמי בעי, L'achilah nami
baye, that
even for eating you need ראשו ורובו. Rosho v'rubo. So why did
it talk about firstborn? Talk about eating? Because ובכורה איצטריכא, U'bechorah itztricha,
because it needed to tell me that head and majority is enough
for the firstborn. I might have thought that's not even sufficient. סלקא
דעתך אמינא, Salka dach'tach amina, I might have thought הוה כתיב אך
בכור שור. Hava k'siv ach bechor shor. However the firstborn of an
ox, עד שיהא שור ובכורו שור, Ad sheyei shor u'bechoro shor, that
it really emphasizes that the firstborn has to really look like an
ox. So if that's true maybe even the majority isn't enough. סלקא
דעתך אמינא ולא תיסגי ליה בראשו ורובו. Salka dach'tach amina v'lo tisgi
lei b'rosho v'rubo. Majority and the head doesn't... isn't sufficient. It has
to fully be an ox.
maybe it needs all of it, קא משמע לן Ka Mashma Lan
that that is sufficient. So yes, it jumped to say that head
and majority is enough for the firstborn, because I might have thought
for firstborn it needs to be 100% like the right species, but
that's not to implicitly exclude eating. Eating as well, head and majority
is what you need. So we don't know, it jumped, it leapfrogged
over eating. We don't know for eating whether you need head and
majority or some characteristic suffices.
Yes, I know, the גמרא Gemara says השבינו לנקטס דנובי, Hashivinu Lenaktas
Denovi, we had that before, ונתנו
ליתומים דנובי.
Venatnu Leyetomim
Denovi. Okay, sometimes it does. Moving on. תא שמע, Ta Shema, come
in here. את זה לא תאכלו ממעלה הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה. Et Zeh
Lo Tochlu Mimaleh Hagera Umimafrizei Haparsa. This
you shall not eat from those that regurgitate their cud and split
their hooves. זה אתה אוכל, Zeh Atah Ochel, this is what you
may not eat, but here's the ברייתא. Baraita. זה אתה אוכל, Zeh
Atah Ochel, this is what you may not eat, אבל אתה אוכל
הבא בסימן אחד. Aval Atah Ochel Haba Besiman Echad. So this you
cannot eat, these things like camels and whatever, but you can eat
something that look somewhat like a camel but has some characteristics like
their mother. Now סימן אחד Siman Echad should not be misunderstood, although
in this context it sounds like it, but תוספות Tosafot is quick
to point out we have not said until now, the only question
is some characteristics, we've never emphasized the kosher characteristics. Right, in this
context you could have thought what this means is, is that if
an offspring of a cow looks like a camel, what do you
need for it to be kosher? Maybe it needs to have at
least either split hooves or chew the cud. That fits in the
language here of סימן אחד. Siman Echad. But overall the גמרא Gemara
has been ignoring that and תוספות Tosafot says that we should not
assume that in this context either. And the point here is just,
yes, you can have something that looks like a camel and be
kosher as long as it has some characteristics like the mother. Now
that again is the position within the position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. Because according to the חכמים, Chachamim, who was the according to
the our משנה Mishna or סתם משנה, Stam Mishna, it could be
100% like a camel. If it's the offspring of a cow, it's
kosher. So all of this is only within רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
By the way, for everybody that thinks that these things sound, you
know, sort of fantastical and how would this ever happen, unless maybe
the father was of a different species and how could a father
of a different species, whatever. Anyway, at least you should think that
a relevant application of this גמרא Gemara is the question of creating
these types of animals in a laboratory. Right, does it matter what
the genetically what it is and what the mother is and whatever,
or does it just matter what it looks like? According to רבי
שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, what it looks like really matters. So here within
that content that if it looks like a non-kosher animal it's not
kosher, this ברייתא Baraita says if it has one characteristic like the
mother, it's okay. So you see, it's going to be the point,
you don't need ראשו ורובו. Rosho Verubo. Even one characteristic like the
mother will enough to say that it is kosher. Yes, Charlie.
Well, it is practical because most species of bovine can interbreed with
each other and produce offspring and the children do not look like
the parents.
Do they look like would they look like a non-kosher animal or
they would just look weird?
They were all be kosher, mind
you, they'd all have split hooves and chew their cud.
Right, the beefalo is is the American bison gets interbred with domestic
cattle all the time.
Okay, but you wouldn't go as far as actually looking like a
non-kosher
animal with non-kosher traits. Right, right. Okay, so anyway, yeah, I
just want to say, so even if it doesn't have split hooves,
right, as long as it comes from a cow?
I
mean, it might
not have split hooves because of a birth defect.
Okay, right. Okay, so now let's go on. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, yes?
I'm sorry, when you said one
סימן? Siman? Right, right.
So that's the point. You could have thought from context it meant
it meant the characteristic, the kosher characteristic of chewing the cud or
split hooves. But again, we have yet to say that, we've all
just talked about basic physical characteristics and תוספות Tosafot explicitly says that
don't be misunderstood, you don't don't be misled by that language, although
you know maybe that is the approach of this ברייתא, Baraita, but
if you want to sort of, if you want to level it
with the other discussion, then and then we would assume that it
was not specific in terms of that. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So there you say that one סימן Siman
is enough.
ואלו הן הבא בסימן אחד. Ve-elu Hen Haba Besiman Echad. Did I
skip a line? זה טמא הנולד מן הטהור. Zeh Tamei Hanolad Min
Hatahor. ואלו הן הבא בסימן אחד. Ve-elu Hen Haba Besiman Echad. זה
טמא הנולד
מן הטהור. Zeh Tamei Hanolad Min Hatahor. את זה לא תאכלו ממעלה
הגרה וממפריסי הפרסה. Et Zeh Lo Tochlu Mimaleh Hagera Umimafrizei Haparsa. זה
אתה אוכל, Zeh Atah Ochel, אבל אתה אוכל הבא בסימן אחד. Aval
Atah Ochel Haba Besiman Echad. ואיזה זה הבא בסימן אחד? Ve-eizeh Zeh
Haba Besiman Echad? Okay, that's what I was. What is considered that
it has one סימן? Siman? זה טמא הנולד מן הטהור. Zeh Tamei
Hanolad Min Hatahor. So a non-kosher animal born of a kosher animal.
ועיבורו מן הטהור. Ve-iburo Min Hatahor. Finally answering Michael's question, and even
the father, it became impregnated by a kosher animal. So yes, it
had a kosher mother and a kosher father, and nevertheless it itself
looks non-kosher, and as long as one of the סימנים, Simanim, one
of the character one characteristic is like the mother, it's okay. So
this is within רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, and that if it looks
like non-kosher it's not good, but within there it says one סימן
Siman is enough to save it. Now, יכול אפילו עיבורו מן הטמא?
Yachol Afillu Iburo Min Hatamei? Maybe I would go so far to
even say this even if the father was a non-kosher animal? Right,
how much now does genetics matter regardless of looks? Right, how much
does the father merit? Now, תלמוד לומר, Talmud Lomar, שה כשבים ושה
עזים. Seh Chsavim Vesheh Izim. No, the verse says a sheep of
the plural sheep. and a sheep or whatever, a goat, you know,
a lamb of the plural goats. So it's in the plural, meaning
both parents have to be kosher species, שה אביו כבש ואמו כבשה
seh aviv keves v'imo kivsah until its father is a ram and
its mother is a ewe. דברי רבי יהושע. Divrei Rabbi Yehoshua. That's
Rabbi Yehoshua says. So according to Rabbi Yehoshua and this is again
is assumed all following the Rabbi Shimon approach that what it looks
like matters. He says, first of all for it to be a
kosher species, both parents have to be kosher. Okay, presumably that would
by the way be the even if the offspring looked kosher, there's
a requirement that both parents be kosher. So genetics matters as well
as appearance. But even if both parents are kosher, if it looks
not kosher, it's not kosher unless it has one characteristic. So here
you see within any characteristic presumably, you know, the sheep, the horns,
any characteristic that looks makes it looks like kosher. At least now
we have not been specifying. So within this we're saying within Rabbi
Shimon one characteristic like the mother would be sufficient to save it.
But now we get Rabbi Eliezer's position. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer
omer לא בא הכתוב להתיר את המותר lo ba hakatuv l'hatir es
hamutar when the when we're learning from the verse, right, even this
that looks like non-kosher can be kosher, it's not coming to permit
something that's obviously permissible. If both parents are kosher, then obviously the
offspring is permissible. Okay, so he actually is not so much of
a Rabbi Shimon type of an approach. He says as long as
both parents are kosher it doesn't matter what the offspring looks like
you wouldn't need the verse. At least that's what it sounds like.
Then he says so what is the verse coming to permit? אלא
להוסיף על המותר ela l'hosif al hamutar to add to what is
permitted. ואיזה זה v'eizeh zeh what is that? זה טמא הנולד מן
הטהור ועיבורו מן הטמא. zeh tamei hanolad min hatahor v'iburo min hatamei.
The offspring is not kosher, looks not kosher, and the father is
a not kosher animal. So there I would have thought forget about
what it looks like, this is a half חזיר chazir or whatever
it is, a half camel. Okay, by genetics. So that should so
that should say that that's not good. So therefore in that case
או אינו אלא עיבורו מן הטהור o eino ela iburo min hatahor
maybe it's like you Rabbi Yehoshua are saying that that even if
its father is kosher, if it looks like a not kosher animal
it's a problem. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar שה כשבים ושה עזים seh
kesavim v'seh izim מכל מקום mikol makom קרי ליה kari lei okay
מכל מקום mikol makom שה כשבים ושה עזים seh kesavim v'seh izim
period. I'm sorry. Okay, so no maybe it is מכל מקום. mikol
makom. Yeah, מכל מקום mikol makom period. Okay, so it
says the fact that it says שה seh you emphasized the כשבים
ועזים kesavim v'izim that both parents are kosher, I emphasize שה. seh.
It says שה שה seh seh means any type of an offspring,
any type of a lamb regardless of even if the even if
the father was a non-kosher animal.
So even if it looks entirely non-kosher?
No, well that's not so clear. Okay, how much would he would
Rabbi Eliezer care about looks as well, you know, let's say it
looked totally non-kosher, let's say one from both kosher animals looked totally
non-kosher, right? We don't know how far that position would go. But
at least when he's saying that if it has, you know, that
if basically Rabbi Eliezer's position was, actually Rabbi Yehoshua's position was, if
one parent is not kosher, it's not kosher, you need it to
be fully genetically kosher, and even there, you know, it has to
look a little bit like its mother. And comes along Rabbi Eliezer
and says that Rabbi Eliezer says if both parents are kosher I
don't need it's obviously kosher. Now obviously would even if it completely
looks non-kosher, that I don't know. Maybe. That would stand to reason
but that's not being spelled out. Okay, right. We don't know. We
don't know. But it's right, logically it would be to say if
both parents are kosher I don't care what it looks like, all
I care about is genetics. Okay, but if one of the parents
is not kosher maybe that would be not kosher because then it's
half a טריפה treifa animal and then telling me that even that
is kosher. Okay, so logically yes, Rabbi Eliezer's like the חכמים Chachamim
that we don't care about what it looks like, we only care
about parentage and to go so far to say we don't even
really care about the father, all we care about is the mother.
Okay, but now that's Rabbi Eliezer. Now we're going to go back
and look at I don't know. Now we go back and look
at Rabbi Yehoshua, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says קרי ליה טמא
כרבי שמעון. kari lei tamei k'Rabbi Shimon. So first of all it
calls the animal not kosher, the offspring not kosher, right? It says
if a kosher animal gives birth to a not kosher, meaning and
if it fully looks like a not kosher animal, it will be
considered not kosher. So you see we're working within the position of
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that if the offspring looks fully not kosher,
it's not kosher. וקאמר v'ka'amar and nevertheless it says אבל אתה אוכל
הבא בסימן אחד aval atah ochel haba b'siman echad that one characteristic
like the mother is enough. Okay, that's a very simple point. Meaning
before you even get to fully figuring out Rabbi Eliezer, Rabbi Yehoshua
says look, if it looks fully not kosher, it's not kosher, assuming
both parents are kosher. Nevertheless, fully not kosher is not kosher. סימן
אחד siman echad that one way it's like the mother you're okay.
So you see we're working within the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon that it matters what it looks like and we say סימן
אחד siman echad like the mother is enough. So the גמרא Gemara
says you're right, האי תנא hai tanna but nevertheless that's Rabbi Yehoshua
working within Rabbi Shimon. You don't know what Rabbi Shimon himself would
say. האי תנא סבר לה כוותיה בחדא ופליג עליה
בחדא. Hai Tanna savar leh k'vassay bechada ufalig alei bechada. This תנא
Tanna רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua holds of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that
looking not kosher is not good, but then maybe on his own
he says one סימן siman is enough to make it kosher, one
characteristic. That doesn't prove to you whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon himself
would admit that one characteristic like the mother suffices. Yes.
Didn't רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer live before
רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
Oh, that's a good point. Is that true? I keep on getting...
you're right, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua are
earlier. You're very correct. Yeah, I think they're even the רביי Rebbeim
of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Right. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is
a תלמיד talmid of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Excellent point. Okay, so
you'll have to say what it means is that they hold of
the same position of... they agree with the general approach that what
it looks like matters, but you cannot necessarily ascribe... you're right. So
the language פליג עליה בחדא palig alei bechada is a little bit
imprecise. What it means is, yes, they're within his camp, the camp
of what it looks like matters, but you cannot ascribe the specifics
of their position to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. They say one סימן,
siman, you know, saves it, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon might not
agree with that. Okay, so you're right. The framing is not like
they learned from him and they disagree. They hold that general position,
but you cannot necessarily ascribe their specifics to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
specifically. Okay, so you have רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, actually at least
רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, we'll bracket רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer for now,
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that says what it looks like matters. If
it looks not kosher, not kosher, but one סימן siman is enough.
But that doesn't necessarily tell you what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would
hold. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ואיכא דמתני ואיכא דמקשי מוסיף. Ve'ika de'matni ve'ika de'makshi moseif. Some
sort of ask a question and by asking a question and answering
that leads to the same discussion, but they don't start with our
question about what does רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon hold? They start with
a different question. What's the different question? I was waiting for Charlie
to ask this because the discussion was about, well, is the father
a kosher animal or a non-kosher animal? That suggests that a kosher
and a non-kosher animal can mate. But the גמרא Gemara says that
that's not possible for a kosher and non-kosher. And they're correct. So
let's take a look. So some ask and answer. Let's take a
look.
ואיכא... Ve'ika... so let's take a look at that. עיבורא מן הטמא.
Ibura min hatamei. So it says, so according to רבי יהושע, Rabbi
Yehoshua, it says if the father was not kosher, it goes without
saying it's not kosher. And then רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says, no,
even if the father's not kosher, it could be kosher. So the
גמרא Gemara says: מי מעברה? Mi ma'avrah? How could you have an
offspring of a kosher and non-kosher animal? והאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי,
Ve'amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, doesn't רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi say: לעולם אין מתעברת, Le'olam ein misaberes,
you can never get an animal pregnant, לא טמאה מן הטהורה ולא
טהורה מן הטמא, lo tmeia min hatahora velo tahora min hatamei, not
by crossbreeding kosher and non-kosher regardless of which is the female, which
is the male, ולא גסה מן הדקה ולא דקה מן הגסה, velo
gassa min hadakka velo dakka min hagassa, not from large animals meaning
things like cows and camels and horses, that's גסה, gassa, דקה dakka
is like the grazing animals, sheep and goats, so not by crossing
those, which again regardless of which is the mother, which is the
male, which is the
female, ולא בהמה מן החיה ולא חיה מן הבהמה, velo behema min
hachaya velo chaya min habehema, and not a חיה chaya which is
non-domesticated species with בהמה behema domesticated and vice versa, except, however, חוץ
מרבי אליעזר ומחלוקתו. chutz mi-Rabbi Eliezer machlokto. That I have to admit,
says רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, not everybody agrees
with because if you remember the whole discussion of our friend the
כוי, koy, which we're going to spend a lot of time with
in בכורות Bechoros as well, right? So there was a question about
what exactly a כוי koy was, but there was an opinion that
it was a cross between a חיה chaya and a
בהמה. behema. So according to they who believe that a כוי koy
is a cross between a חיה chaya and a בהמה, behema, they
believe a חיה chaya and a בהמה behema can crossbreed,
but otherwise we would not say that.
Okay. שהיו אומרים חיה מתעברת מן הבהמה. Shehayu omrim chaya misaberes min
habehema.
They would say that a חיה chaya can become pregnant from a
בהמה. behema. Fine. So now we've got a question. How could רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer say that the offspring of a חיה chaya and
a בהמה, behema, if the father is not kosher, the offspring is
still kosher? How could the father not be kosher? So the גמרא
Gemara says: ואמר רבי ירמיה דאעבר מקלוט בן פרה. Ve'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah
de'abir mi-kolut ben parah. When רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says the father
was not kosher, he didn't mean really not kosher. He meant not
kosher because it was the offspring of a kosher animal, but it
itself was a קלוט, kolut, had non-split hooves. So you had something
looking like a camel that was an offspring of a cow, because
it was an offspring of a cow, of two cows, whatever, because
it was an offspring of a cow, it really looks not kosher,
but it could mate with another cow because it really genetically is
a cow. Okay, but the important point is it itself halachically is
not kosher. It can mate because genetically it's a cow, but halachically
because it looks like a camel, it's not kosher. So here we
see by the way according to this read that even רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer agrees that if it fully looks like a camel, it's
not kosher. Okay.
Can you say that one more time? So this is... what is
our case? Our case is let's say the mother was like a
perfectly
good cow and a bull gave birth to something that looked like
a camel. So biologically, genetically it's a cow. Therefore it will be
able or bull, it'll be... be able to mate with another cow.
But because it looks like a camel, הלכתית halachically it's not כשר.
kosher. So now we can have a scenario where you have an
offspring of a כשר, kosher, non-כשר kosher animal. How do they mate?
Because even the non-כשר kosher father is biologically a cow. But הלכתית
halachically it's not כשר kosher because it looks like a camel. So
because it's biologically a
cow it's able to mate with a cow, and it's able to
produce an offspring, but because it looks like a camel it's not
כשר kosher and now we want to know what is the status
of the child.
So קלוט kalut means does it mean like having one hoof? Yes.
So it doesn't necessarily mean that so you're saying it looks like
a camel.
Yes, because having one hoof is not enough. We said it had
to fully look like the other. That's our question, how much does
it have to look like?
So if it was a cow that gave birth to a cow
of uncloven hooves, that's not considered טמא. tamei.
Well, that's the question about ראש ורובו rosh verubo etc. presumably not.
So anyway, the גמרא Gemara says like this, דיעבר מכולהו בן פרה.
de'avar mikulhu ben parah. דאיהו בדברי רבי שמעון קאמר de'ihu bedivrei Rabbi
Shimon ka'amar and all of this even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because
Michael was right before, you could have said that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer completely doesn't care about what it looks like. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer says as long as both parents are כשר kosher it's okay,
even if only the mother is כשר kosher it's okay, and who
cares what it looks like? But now we're saying not that way.
We're saying that according even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer admits that if
it fully looks like a camel it's not כשר kosher and that
allows him to discuss his scenario of a כשר kosher and non-כשר
kosher animal mating. Okay? So we're within רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דקאמר
אבל אתה אוכל הבא בסימן אחד. deka'amar aval atah ochel haba besiman
echad. Okay, and therefore we are saying
that now that we figured that out, now we figured out that
when we're talking about the mating, we're saying that you can eat
the we're talking about a non-כשר kosher animal, I mean about an
animal that is a cow biologically but it looks like a camel
non-כשר. kosher. So we're all within רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and within
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon we have the opinion of רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua that says if it has one כשר kosher סימן, siman, it's
okay. So you see within רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon camp even one
כשר kosher סימן siman is enough. And then it has the same
answer. האי תנא סבר לה כוותיה בחדא ופליג עליה בחדא. Hai tanna
savar lah kavateih bechada ufalig aleih bechada. This you cannot prove that
this is exactly רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. It's in רבי שמעון's Rabbi
Shimon approach that if it looks non-כשר kosher it's not כשר, kosher,
but not the details. Here we know that one סימן siman is
enough to be okay. We don't know exactly what רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon would say. Okay, so now we have what do we have?
So we have the following. We have the position of רבי שמעון,
Rabbi Shimon, which we reject להלכה, lehalacha, but is very important for
all these questions about laboratory-created animals, which says if it looks non-כשר
kosher it's not כשר. kosher. Within the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon approach,
we say what does it need, how much does it have to
look כשר kosher to be כשר? kosher? Here we have רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua saying one characteristic, in the context
by the way that one characteristic sounds like a כשר kosher characteristic,
although תוספות Tosafot downplay that. And but then we say it's possible
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon himself would demand even more than that, would
demand the predominantly it looks כשר. kosher. Beyond the question of what
it looks like, we have the question of parentage. Okay, whereas רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says as soon as the father is not כשר,
kosher, however you create that scenario, then that automatically puts it off,
you know, says that it's not כשר. kosher. If it's half of
a non-כשר kosher animal genetically, biologically it's not כשר. kosher. And רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer seems not to care about the father, only matters
the mother. So now the גמרא Gemara is going to explore that
question. Let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
למימרא דרבי אליעזר סבר זה וזה גורם מותר ורבי יהושע סבר זה
וזה גורם אסור. Lemeimra deRabbi Eliezer savar zeh vezeh gorem mutar veRabbi
Yehoshua savar zeh vezeh gorem assur. So the idea of how is
a child created, right? It's created by two causes, the mother and
the father. Also God, but okay now we're following just biologically, right,
there are three partners in the creation of anybody, but here we're
talking about the animals. So anyway, the mother and the father. So
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says זה וזה גורם, zeh vezeh gorem, the
mother caused and the father caused, מותר, mutar, as long as even
though one of the causes is a forbidden cause, the father, you
can ignore it as long as the mother is the כשר kosher
species, that's sufficient. And רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua is of the opinion
זה וזה גורם אסור. zeh vezeh gorem assur. No, as long even
if you have two causes, if one of them is problematic, the
father is not כשר, kosher, it is forbidden. That's what emerges from
our previous ברייתא. braita. והאיפכא שמעינן להו. Veha'ipcha shameinan lehu. We know
that in general they hold the reverse position. Because what did we
teach? ולד טריפה, Velad tereifah, the offspring of a טריפה. tereifah. Okay,
so the mother is a טריפה. tereifah. Here it's the reverse, the
mother is not כשר kosher because she's a טריפה, tereifah, and the
father would be let's say a non-טריפה, tereifah, כשר kosher animal. So
what is the story of that? רבי אליעזר אומר לא יקרב לגבי
מזבח ורבי יהושע אומר יקרב לגבי מזבח. Rabbi Eliezer omer lo yikarev
legabei mizbe'ach veRabbi Yehoshua omer yikarev legabei mizbe'ach. Now the animal itself
is not a טריפה tereifah
because although we have said יוצא מן הטמא טמא yotzei min hatamei
tamei for example and if you milk a טריפה tereifah cow, טריפה
tereifah just literally means an injured טריפה tereifah cow, the milk is
not כשר, kosher, but once an animal alive animal is born, it
has its own status. So even if its mother was a טריפה,
tereifah, it would not be. However, let's say we're not talking about
can I eat it, but can I bring it as a sacrifice?
I sanctified the mother, the mother is a טריפה, tereifah, and then
she gives birth. So the sanctity of the child is only a
derived sanctity from the mother. So therefore, there if we only focused
on the mother, the child would not be able to be brought
as a sacrifice. Because it's deriving its sanctity from a sanctity that
cannot be brought as a sacrifice from an animal that's a טריפה.
treifa. So you understand why that is conceptually different than the question
of כשרות. kashrut. Once it's born, I treat it as its own
animal and if it's not טריפה treifa it's not a problem, but
in terms of its קדושה, kedusha, the קדושה kedusha derives from the
mother. And if the mother's a טריפה, treifa, therefore its sanctity also
would not let it be brought on the altar.
You could sanctify it
separately, but here the question is it became sanctified only through the
mother. Okay,
well there's a question also once it's sanctified can you add another
sanctity on it, but in theory if it hadn't been sanctified from
the first from the outset, correct. Okay, so רבי אליעזר אומר לא
יקרב ולא יעלה בין מזבח, Rabbi Eliezer omer lo yikarev velo yaaleh
bin mizbeach, do not bring it on the altar, right, because the
fact that the mother is has a problem is enough of a
problem. And רבי יהושע אומר יקרב ויעלה בין מזבח, Rabbi Yehoshua omer
yikarev veyaaleh bin mizbeach, you can bring it on the altar because
the father wasn't a טריפה treifa even though the mother was. And
presumably they're flipping their position whether you know whether one parent is
good enough to salvage it or you need both parents. So the
גמרא Gemara says באלמא סבר רבי אליעזר זה וזה גורם אסור. be'alma
savar Rabbi Eliezer zeh vezeh gorem assur. רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer general
position is not like the first thing we quoted, it's like the
second
thing, that if one is a problem it's a problem. That's why
when the mother's a טריפה, treifa, the animal can't be brought as
a קרבן. korban. ושני הכא ve'shani hacha here by the kosher animals,
only the mother suffices, why? דאם כן לכתוב קרא כשבים ועזים. de'im
ken lichtov kra ksavim ve'izim. Says let it write the lamb of
sheep and goats. שה שה למה לי? seh seh lama li? Why
does it say the word שה seh twice? So שמע מינה שה
מכל מקום, shema mina seh mikol makom, whatever type of a lamb
regardless of what the father is as long as the mother's okay.
So this is an exception. Normally if one parent has a problem
it's a problem, here we just go by the mother. And the
reverse by רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. ורבי יהושע
אמר לך,
ve'Rabbi Yehoshua
amar lach, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would say to you, באלמא זה
וזה גורם מותר. be'alma zeh vezeh gorem mutar. Normally I would say
that if one parent is okay, it's good enough, that's sufficient. We
ignore the problematic parent. והכא, ve'hacha, if that were true here, דאם
כן לכתוב קרא שור שה כשבים ועז. de'im ken lichtov kra shor
seh ksavim ve'iz. Don't write in the plural כשבים ועזים. ksavim ve'izim.
כשבים ועזים למה לי? ksavim ve'izim lama li? Why does it say
in the plural, sheeps and goats? שמע מינה עד דאבי כבש ואמו
כבשה shema mina ad de'avi keves ve'imo kivsa to tell you that
both parents have to be kosher. Normally I would have said one
is enough, here I need both. So they're basically saying you're right,
their positions have reversed themselves, this case is an exception where they
take the opposite positions but in general they say in general they're
flipped. Now the interesting thing here is is that here it does
not give any greater weight to the father over the mother. זה
וזה גורם, zeh vezeh gorem, actually the case of the sanctity, the
only reason the animal was okay was because the father wasn't a
טריפה. treifa. That was enough. Normally though, we emphasize in terms of
you know this issue about the offspring, the mother is always seen
as key. Not only that, even רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says
that it doesn't matter who the father is if the mother is
kosher, he never said the opposite, it doesn't matter who the mother
is if the father is kosher. So it's a little funny first
of all the way the גמרא Gemara is abstracting it to זה
וזה גורם zeh vezeh gorem and not emphasizing the mother and by
the way the גמרא Gemara actually has an exact term to refer
to this question of does the father matter in determining the nature
of the offspring, which is חוששים לזרע האב או לא, chosheshim lezera
ha'av o lo, does it matter the father's contribution, the זרע האב
zera ha'av in terms of the sort of species identification or the
halakhic status of the offspring. So תוספות Tosafot raises the question why
the גמרא Gemara here framed it in this much more abstract way
when it really should have been framed in the more sort of
natural sort of category we have for this discussion which is חוששים
לזרע האב. chosheshim lezera ha'av.
So take a look at the תוספות ואיפכא Tosafot ve'ipcha he tries
to distinguish between those two, but I just wanted to point out
that this normally we would have put it in that discussion not
in a more generic זה וזה גורם. zeh vezeh gorem. Now the
גמרא Gemara wraps this up, but we haven't yet answered our question
according to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon does one characteristic is that sufficient
or not? תא שמע ta shema come and hear, הנולד מן הפרה,
hanolad min hapara, so we have a ברייתא baraita I'm sorry, we
have a ברייתא baraita I'm sorry I skipped a line. רבי שמעון
אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, we have a ברייתא baraita that is going
to be explicit. גמל גמל שתי פעמים, gamal gamal shtei pe'amim, it
says גמל gamal twice, אחד גמל הנולד מן הגמל, echad גמל hanolad
min hagamal, whether a camel born from a camel's not kosher, ואחד
גמל הנולד מן הפרה, ve'echad gamal hanolad min hapara, even a camel
from a cow if it looks like a camel it's not kosher.
And then he says ואם ראשו ורובו דומה לאמו מותר באכילה. ve'im
rosho verubo domeh le'imo mutar ba'achila. If the head and the majority
if it predominantly looks like the mother it's kosher. שמע מינה shema
mina from here it's clear לאכילה נמי בעי רבי שמעון ראש ורובו,
le'achila nami ba'ei Rabbi Shimon rosh verubo, even for eating he requires
that it predominantly looks like the mother, one characteristic is not enough,
שמע מינה. shema mina. What about the father? So we don't know,
we don't know how he fits into that debate of the father.
So again what do we have? Assuming both parents are of the
right species biologically it's a hundred percent cow or sheep or whatever,
does the way it look matter? So there's רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and his camp, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that says yes, if it looks not kosher it's
not good, and then the question is well not necessarily רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer but רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, whatever it looks not kosher
it's not good. And then the question is how much does it
have to look כשר? kosher? רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua says even one
סימן, siman, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon himself says it has to look
predominantly כשר. kosher. That was in the camp that it matters how
it looks. Then there's another question about does it matter who the
father is regardless of how it looks. And there רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua says it matters who the father is, if it's not כשר
kosher automatically it's not כשר, kosher, and רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
no, it only matters who the mother is. Maybe you can have
some combination of those two things, but anyway it's easier to think
about them as separate concerns. Yes, Charles.
So רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua would say, just let me make sure
I'm getting it all straight, that if the, let's say you have
a cow that had cloven hooves instead of split hooves, and it
gives birth to a
and it mates with a cow, so then
and its offspring looks like
a also has cloven hooves and it's not כשר, kosher, right?
Because cloven hooves is not enough. Even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
for it to be not כשר kosher it has to be, it
has to be predominantly not כשר. kosher. If it's predominantly כשר kosher
and just the hooves issue, I don't think even for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that would make it טמא. tamei. Right, it would only
be טמא tamei if it predominantly looked like a camel. Okay, and
that's how you could get a scenario of the father being not
כשר kosher is if it predominantly looked like a camel.
It doesn't mean that it's limited to that.
No, that's just a what do you call it? Yeah, exactly.
Now moving up, היוצא מן הטמא טמא. hayotzei min hatamei tamei. Now
we get back to the I think the thing that's more relevant
for us, which we had the discussion before about milk of a
camel and now we're also getting into a more general discussion. Things
that come from non-כשר. kosher. So not just offspring of non-כשר kosher
animals are non-כשר, kosher, but products of non-כשר kosher animals are non-כשר.
kosher. We discussed already milk, let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes.
Before it gets to honey, we have another interesting type of a
product. So בעי מיניה מרב ששת. baei minei meiRav Sheshet. They asked
רב ששת, Rav Sheshet, מי רגליים של חמור מהו? mei raglayim shel
chamor mahu? Urine, donkey urine. Apparently donkey urine was actually drunk for
maybe medicinal purposes and they wanted to know, is it כשר? kosher?
Okay, now ותיבעי
להו, vetibaei lehu, so why not ask maybe health purposes, I'm not
going to get into that. ותיבעי להו, vetibaei lehu, why not ask
the question about דסוסים וגמלים? desusim vegamalin? How about urine of horses
and camels? No, דסוסים וגמלים לא מיבעי להו. desusim vegamalin lo mibaei
lehu. That we're not asking. דלא אכירי, delo achiri, those are not
sort of smelly, meaning basically those basically look like clear water and
or they're not, אכירי achiri can also mean like cloudy or something
like that, meaning that's basically clear water. So therefore we don't consider
it a product of the animal. We just consider that the liquid
that came in went out and we don't consider it to have
been transformed. You can drink that, that's basically just water. One minute,
ולא
דמו לחלב, velo damu lechalav, it's not like milk. We've already established
camel milk is not כשר, kosher, but the idea we're assuming is
that that's because it's a product. Now I should say by the
way, this conversation is also taking place in the context of the
next משנה mishna which we haven't read. The next משנה mishna says
if you open up a non-כשר kosher fish and see כשר kosher
fish inside that it swallowed, those כשר kosher fish are כשר. kosher.
If you open up a כשר kosher fish and see non-כשר kosher
fish inside, those non-כשר kosher fish are non-כשר. kosher. The fish that
are in the stomach are not considered a product, okay, of the
animal just because they happen to be inside of it. So there
on the one hand milk of a non-כשר kosher is not כשר,
kosher, on the other hand something that was ingested by an animal
is not defined by the animal. So what degree is something considered
a product or something is just passing through? Okay, so that we
want to know here about urine. So if it's a clear, if
the urine is basically clear and not smelly, it's basically water in,
water out, it's like the fish that come into the fish and
it's not a product. But maybe if it's smelly and it transforms,
maybe that is considered to be a product. Yes, Charles.
This is not theoretical, there's a very commonly prescribed drug called Premarin
that comes from horse urine.
Very interesting. Okay, there you go. Now Michael throws in an interesting
question about whether something is taken for medicinal purposes is אכילה, achila,
but we're going to bracket all of that. So let's take a
look. So okay, ולא, so the גמרא Gemara says therefore if it's
clear it's not like milk. And therefore it's not a product. מיא
עול מיא נפק, maya o maya nafak,
water in, water out.
מי כי קמיבעי להו, mi ki kamibaei lehu, what's our question? דחמור,
dechamor, okay, urine of a donkey, דאכירי, deachiri, which is like spoiled,
smelly, and cloudy, and דמו לחלב, damu lechalav, it's like milk. Not
meaning edible like milk, but meaning that it's been transformed by the
animal. מאי, mai, what do we say?
מגופיה קמימצי
מימצצי, miguffei kamimtzi mimtzatzi, does it sort of get produced, sort of
squeezed out through the body? Does it get produced by the body?
ואסירי, vaasiri, and it's
forbidden, אודילמא מיא עול מיא נפק, odiama maya o maya nafak, no,
there too, water in, water out. והא דאכירי, veha deachiri, so why
is it sort of like rotten, smelly, cloudy? הבלא דבישרא הוא, havla
debisra hu, that's because it gets sort of the, you know, the
air of the meat. So you know, you pass through a smelly
place, you get smelly, but it didn't really get transformed. Basically it's
water that just collected the smells of the animal, but it wasn't
actually transformed. formed by the animal. So that alright, so that we're
going to ask. Anyway, that was our question. Okay, so but it's
important that conceptually, it's not anything that comes out of an animal,
right? It has to be considered produced by the animal. And obviously
a lot of things it produces are because it takes stuff in
and then transforms them. So אמר ליה רב ששת, Amar lei Rav
Sheshet, Rav Sheshet said תניתוה, tanituha, we learned it in our משנה.
Mishna.
היוצא מן הטמא טמא והיוצא מן הטהור טהור. Ha-yotzei min ha-tamei tamei
ve-ha-yotzei min ha-tahor tahor. Okay, what comes out of something non-kosher is
non-kosher. מי טמא לא קאמר אלא מן הטמא. Mei tamei lo ka-amar
ela min ha-tamei. It didn't say from the non-kosher, but מן הטמא,
min ha-tamei, which if you were to ask us, we would say
doesn't that mean the exact same thing? But the גמרא Gemara thinks
it suggests something different.
מן הטמא והני נמי מינא דטמא הוא. Min ha-tamei ve-hanei nami mina
de-tamei hu. And this is also of the species of the tamei.
Somehow it understands that מי הטמא mei ha-tamei would have suggested more
like it has to be actually a part of the animal itself.
מן הטמא min ha-tamei suggests more that it is a product of
the animal. But you know, the funny thing is that even if
you distinguish between part of the animal and a product of the
animal, the whole question here is, is this a product or not?
Or is this just water in, water out? So it's not exactly
clear how it, how the גמרא Gemara thinks that that answers the
question. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve-ika de-amri, others say, others say what?
It would be non-kosher.
It would be non-kosher because somehow מן הטמא min ha-tamei suggests even
something that is not intrinsically part of the animal, more of a
product. But again, the question is, but is it a product or
is it just water in, water out? So the גמרא Gemara says
ואיכא דאמרי, ve-ika de-amri, some said that the question went so far
to ask even by horses and camels. דסוסיא וגמלא נמי, De-susya ve-gamla
nami, I'm sorry, not, I'm sorry, let me say that here's why
we didn't ask by horses and camels. דסוסיא וגמלא לא קמיבעיא להו.
De-susya ve-gamla lo ka-mibaya lehu. Why did we not ask about horses
and camels? דלא שתו אינשי. De-lo shatu inshi. There you go, because
not because it wouldn't be considered a product, but just because normal
people would never drink it, and therefore it was like a moot
point. Why bother asking? Maybe if you would drink it, you'd be
פטור patur because it would be like, you know, בטלה דעתו אצל
כל אדם, batla da'ato eitzel kol adam, you wouldn't even consider it
food if normal people never eat it. כי קמיבעיא להו, Ki ka-mibaya
lehu, so therefore it was, the only reason we didn't ask was
just because it was moot. When did we ask? דחמרא, De-chamra, about
a donkey. דשתו אינשי, De-shatu inshi, that people drink it, and here
we get for the health purposes, ומעלי לירקונא, u-ma'alei le-yerakona, and it's
helpful for jaundice. Okay, Charlie, any truth to that? Do we know
medically, donkey urine for jaundice? Okay, מאי, mai, what's the story? So
therefore here, the important point about this reframing was that it's not
conceding the point of water in, water out. It's just saying we
didn't ask horses and donkeys because it was moot, which obviously means
that we're going to be more inclined to have a broader definition
of what it means to be a
product, okay, because we're not even conceding the basic point about water
in, water out by the other animals. So אמר ליה רב ששת,
amar lei Rav Sheshet, so Sheshet says תניתוה, tanituha, we learned it
in our משנה, Mishna, היוצא מן הטמא טמא והיוצא מן הטהור טהור,
ha-yotzei min ha-tamei tamei ve-ha-yotzei min ha-tahor tahor, והני נמי מן הטמא
קא אתו. ve-hanei nami min ha-tamei ka atu. These also come from
the non-kosher. Now you understand the answer better, because here we're not
saying is this considered produced or not produced, we're fundamentally sort of,
we're never questioning that. So therefore, well, once it's produced, end of
story, you never even question whether it, whether it's in the category
of being produced.
Okay, so now, so therefore you can't drink it.
You cannot drink it, exactly.
Okay, so the people who drink it, they really can't.
Well, people means, you know, maybe the non-Jews or whatever, okay. All
right, so now that the גמרא Gemara is saying that, now we
have the, now we have accepted this idea of a broader definition
of what it means to be produced. But again, remember, the next
משנה Mishna we are not saying anything inside, you know, that was
once in a non-kosher animal, because the next משנה Mishna speaks about
kosher fish and, you know, that are in the stomach of a
non-kosher fish. So we still acknowledge that there are some things that
are not considered produced by a non-kosher animal, and this gets us
now to the question of bee honey. So here we go. So
the גמרא Gemara says like this. מיתיבי, Meitivei,
they ask a challenge. מפני מה אמרו דבש דבורים מותר? Mipnei mah
amru devash devorim mutar? Why is bee honey permissible? מפני שמכניסות אותן
לגופן, Mipnei she-machnisot otan le-gufan, because they put it into their body,
ואין ממצות אותן מגופן, ve-ein mematzot otan mi-gufan, and they do not
produce it from their body. So I actually looked up last night
how bee honey is made. Very interesting. What they do is they
take the nectar from the flowers, and it actually goes into a
separate stomach, which is a non-digestive stomach, that is basically was described
on this website as a backpack essentially, and it goes all straight
into this stomach which is just held there, it is not digested
at all. They go into the hive, then they're weighted down with
it, so they immediately get, it gets offloaded. They transfer it mouth
to mouth to the other bees, who then what the bees do
is, is that they add some some type of enzyme or whatever
and put it on the wall of the hive, and then eventually
it evaporates and becomes honey. So if you think about it, really
it does not get transformed in the bees itself. It gets into
their body, stored in their body, but it gets transformed outside of
their body.
But they add the enzyme.
But it's outside, from what I understood from this website, Charlie can
double check it, he's looking there now, but from what I understood
the enzyme was added outside of their body, that they, that they
pass it from their stomach, it sort of gets... held by the
bee maybe in their mouth a little bit, they add in the
enzyme and they immediately like stick it on the wall.
So if that's what, it's expelled from the body before the transformation.
Exactly. The transformation takes place on...
Right. Now some of the transformation might be like in the mouth,
the enzymes might be, I didn't get that fully in the mouth,
but it was never like fully into the body and became something
else. When enzyme was added to the mix and it was put
on the... in the mouth? I know, but if let's say I
give you an example, let's say I gave my apple to a
camel and the camel chewed it and spat in it and then
I took it out, right, would it be not כשר, kosher, would
that be like something produced by the camel? Right, so that's the...
so it's not really...
they're not taking in honey. Right. They're taking in nectar.
But they're not producing honey. They're putting in enzyme and they're sticking
it on the wall of the hive and after it evaporates it
turns to honey. So nothing in their body transforms it.
Why does it...
where does the enzyme come from? What?
That, right, the enzyme that they contribute comes from... Anyway, I think
I think we can understand why it's an interesting question whether it's
considered to be produced by the bees, so therefore it transformed in
their body. Okay, yes they make it, but do they make it
in their body? Is it a product of their body? Okay, so
that's what we say. Now why is that a question? The question
is, as the גמרא Gemara assumes that that cannot be any less
than urine. Okay, so how come here it says it's not a
problem? So if that's not a problem, urine also shouldn't be a
problem. Okay, now not necessarily, maybe urine is transformed more, but anyway
the גמרא Gemara assumes that it should be no less than urine.
So as גמרא Gemara says, who's the אמר? amar? דרבי יעקב. De-Rabbi
Yaakov. He would say like רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov who says the
reason bee honey is not a problem is a different reason. דאמר
דובשא רחמנא שרייה. De-amar duvsha Rachmana shareya.
It's a special exception. Fundamentally bee honey is a problem and is
produced by a non-כשר kosher animal and urine therefore which is similar
to that is a problem. And why can we eat bee honey?
The תורה Torah gave us a specific waiver by bee honey. How
do you know that? דתניא, De-tanya, we תנא ברייתא, tana baraita, רבי
יעקב אומר, Rabbi Yaakov omer, אך זה תאכלו מכל שרץ העוף, ach
ze tochlu mi-kol sheretz ha-of, this is what you shall eat from
all of the, you know, sort of... you should not eat, excuse
me, right, from the flying whatever the flying crawling things like the
insects. זה תאכל ואי אתה אוכל שרץ עוף טמא. Ze ta'ochel ve-i
ata ochel sheretz of tamei. No, אך זה תאכלו, ach ze tochlu,
not לא תאכלו. lo tochlu. תאכלו, Tochlu, right, it was about the
grasshoppers I think. Okay, so anyway, flying שרץ sheretz is basically like
the grasshoppers. So it says this you can eat, but you can't
eat a non-כשר kosher bug. So גמרא Gemara says why do you...
what type of דרשה drasha is that? Of course you can't eat
a non-כשר kosher bug. שרץ עוף טמא בהדיא כתיב. Sheretz of tamei
be-hedya ktiv. That's explicit in the תורה. Torah. אלא, Ela, here's what
the דרשה drasha means. שרץ עוף טמא אתה אוכל, Sheretz of tamei
ata ochel, the inference is you can eat the כשר kosher bugs,
locusts, don't eat the non-כשר kosher ones, but אבל אתה אוכל מה
שעוף טמא משריץ. aval ata ochel ma she-of tamei mashritz. You can
eat one... you can eat... it's only the non-כשר kosher bugs you
can't eat. You can eat a product of the non-כשר kosher insect,
a specific product, not all products. What product can you eat? Bee
honey. ואיזה זה? זה דבש דבורים. Ve-eizeh ze? Ze dvash devorim. That's
bee honey. So it's a funny דרשה drasha exactly how he gets
it, but the point is he learns that fundamentally it should be
טרף, treif, but it is a specific exception that the תורה Torah
has given us. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says יכול אף דבש
הגיזים והצירים? yakhol af dvash hagizim ve-hatzirim? Maybe even other types of
honey from these other types of insects. I don't know how they
translate those things. I mean a צירעה tzirah is a hornet. Do
hornets have honey? Like
wasps. Wasps have honey?
I don't... I've never heard of that.
Now there is a problem, I should let you know, that the...
especially Red Delicious apple, they... they smear with... wax from a... I
think wasp or hornet. Okay, so... I believe. You can go ahead
and check that. Or they used to. Or sometimes they would. They
used to maybe. Anyway, so the point there is is that even
though bee honey is כשר, kosher, things that are products of wasps
and hornets or whatever are not כשר. kosher. Okay, well, that's the
question. According to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, it's because the תורה Torah
gives you a particular exception for honey. But it's the one exception.
Everything else falls into the general rule.
But they also have the process where it comes from...
No, that's the גמרא's Gemara dealing with. One approach says it's not
really produced by the bees. Then you would have to say that
the wax is produced differently than the honey. I didn't get a
chance to check that out. But the other approach says fundamentally bee
honey should be אסור. assur. It's a particular
allowance. The תורה Torah knew you couldn't exist half ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah without honey. So therefore you were allowed honey, but it was
the one exception. Everything else remains
forbidden. What? The wash-off?
Yeah. And I also think that they haven't been doing that for
a while. Okay, anyway. Okay, אמרת לא. amarta lo. ומה ראית לרבות
דבורים ולהוציא הגיזים והצירים? U-mah ra'ita le-rabot devorim u-le-hotzi hagizim ve-hatzirim? Why
did you only include bee honey and exclude these other honeys or
who knows, waxes from hornets and wasps? מרבה אני דבש דבורים שאין
להם שם לוואי. Marbe ani dvash devorim she-ein lahem shem livai.
I allow bee honey that has no... that has no accompanying name.
Meaning honey means bee honey. You don't need a qualifier. So therefore,
if the Torah is going to permit something, it's going to permit
the standard honey. ומוציא אני דבש הגזין וצירים, U'motzi ani devash agazin
v'tzirim,
hornet honey or wasp honey if such a thing exists, שיש לו
שם לוואי, she'yesh lo shem livai, that has a qualifying name and
therefore it's not the standard. So if the Torah's now again so
funny, the Torah never said honey is permissible that I should say
that it's limited to standard honey and not to honey variants. I
only learn it from a דרשה drasha that non-kosher insects are not
kosher, a product is kosher. And somehow I'm going to say but
but anyway according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the assumption is the
product means what would be the primary product of insects? If I
would ask you what's the primary product of insects that you would
want to eat, the answer is honey. And therefore it's only standard
honey and nothing else. That's רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So however he
gets it, the point is it's an exception, but he fundamentally he
says it is considered a product. So what's really at stake here
is how do we define what is a product? One approach says
urine isn't a product, honey isn't a product, those things are fundamentally
not transformed. It has to fundamentally be transformed. And the other approach
says it is a product, urine is אסור, assur, honey has a
special waiver. Let's just finish this point Charlie and then I'll take
your your question. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: כמאן
אזלא הא דתניא, K'man azla ha d'tanya, who's it going that which
we taught in the ברייתא? Beraita? דבש הגזין וצירים טהור ומוותר באכילה,
Devash agazin v'tzirim tahor u'mutar b'achila, that the honey of these wasps
and whatever is טהור, tahor, meaning it's not yet considered food because
why is it not food? Because most people don't eat it. So
unless you plan on eating it, it's not food. Okay, but but
if you do want to eat it, מותר באכילה, mutar b'achila, you
can eat it. דלא כרבי יעקב, D'lo k'Rabbi Yaakov, it's not like
רבי יעקב. Rabbi Yaakov. רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov has a single exception
which is bee honey. But according to the other approach that honey
is not defined as being produced, so the same way honey is
honey of bees isn't produced by the bee, honey of whatever these
other insects are, wasps and whatever, are also not considered produced.
Okay, so therefore
well wax might be might be produced, I don't know how wax
is the wax is made. Okay, so this is it's very important
here the conceptual question. We start with the knowledge that bee honey
is permissible. So there we learn out the rule that what is
defined as something as what does it mean to be produced by
an animal? The way honey is made is not considered to be
produced and therefore it would have implications for wasp honey would be
okay, that urine would be okay, all of those are not produced.
Or do we say that's a single exception, don't learn anything from
that, everything else that basically comes out of an animal is considered
produced by the animal and is not kosher. So there's major differences
which approach you take. Let's get up to the משנה Mishna and
then I will take your question Charlie. The גמרא Gemara says like
this: Okay, תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, we taught similarly about
this issue about טהור. tahor. דבש בכוורתו מטמא טומאת אוכלין שלא במחשבה.
Devash b'kivrato metame tumat ochlin shelo b'machshava. Normal honey even in the
in the in the hive is considered to be foodstuff even if
you do not plan on eating it because normal people will eat
honey, so you don't need to specifically intend to eat it to
give it a status of food. But the point that this is
supporting is the idea that that's normal honey, whereas wasp honey, hornet
honey, or whatever those insects are, those actually would not be considered
food, this is for טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah purposes not for כשרות,
kashrut, unless you plan on eating it because most people don't eat
it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. הני ביני דחמרתא.
Hani beini d'chamarta. So סברו רבנן למימר ביעי נינהו. savru rabanan l'meimar
beici ninhu. So there apparently were certain things that female donkeys would
expel
from you know coming out of their womb at least it was
understood that would look like eggs. Now that might be what are
the things that people can pass? Gallstones? Do people pass kidney stones?
Right. How do you pass a kidney stone? Through through through urine.
Okay, so that makes sense. So it could very well be that
this is the גמרא Gemara is talking about kidney stones. But the
but they wanted to understand what it was, how they identified, and
the question is maybe is it kosher or not even though it's
coming from a donkey? Again, what does it mean to be produced?
So we know that it's a kidney stone then of course it's
not kosher because that's what it is because then it's actually part
of the animal itself. But let's see what the גמרא's question is.
Okay, so סברו רבנן למימר ביעי נינהו ואסירין. Savru rabanan l'meimar beici
ninhu v'assirin. The rabbis thought that they were eggs and forbidden. Now
eggs could mean like eggs of a chicken, but of course we're
talking here about a mammal. So רש״י Rashi says it actually means
somewhat like eggs of a what do you call it? What what
what? Oh, רש״י Rashi said like eggs of the male animal that
maybe the way they got into the female was through what when
they were copulating, the actual ביצים, beitzim, the testicles, somehow entered in
and now they're coming back out again, got torn off and are
coming out. So that they would be forbidden not because they were
produced by the donkey but a type of an אבר מן החי.
eiver min hachai. Okay, ואסירין. v'assirin. So אמר רב ספרא: Amar Rav
Safra: זרעא דאיילא הוא דאזיל בתר איילתא. Zar'a d'ayala hu d'azil batar
ayalta. No, that's not what they are. It actually is the semen
one minute of a אייל. ayal. What's an אייל? ayal? Some type
of a kosher animal like a like a like a deer type
of thing, right? Some type of a large deer that was looking
after a איילתא. ayalta. ...to mate with a female deer, with a
doe. ואיידי דרחמה צר לא מזדקקא, Ve-Aidi De-Rachmah Tzar Lo Mizdakeka, because
it had a narrow womb, you know, a genital opening, therefore it
was not or just wasn't in heat, it wasn't interested in mating
with this deer, with this large deer, this
ואזל בתר יחמורתא. Ve-Azal Batar Yachmorta. So then it looked for, it
looked to mate with a, although we know that it can't actually
have offspring, but anyway, it looked to copulate with a female
donkey. ונתרי, Venatri, and this came off, which means that it is
basically dried up semen according to how he understands where this came
from, and as dried up semen it's not not kosher, it's not
actually some of the meat of... so they both think that this
got into this female donkey from a male. One thinks it got
from the male's testicles and therefore is not kosher, and the other
says it got from some dried up semen and therefore is kosher.
But why? Why? Because we believe that it is semen of a,
of a deer, of a kosher animal.
Yes. יחמור Yachmur is listed as a kosher animal in Parshat Re'eh.
Oh, that's a good point. Oh, you're right. I was reading... but
Rashi says, hmm.
Yeah, I mean...
you're right. No, no, you're right. You're right. I stand corrected. You're
right.
Nice call footnote. I know. Yeah, no, no, no.
I stand... I stand corrected. I was reading it as חמור, Chamor,
חמורתא, Chamorta, but it's יחמורתא. Yachmorta. Yeah, but... thank you. I stand
corrected. Anyway, either way though, the... oh, so I guess if that's
true, right, it doesn't matter. Anyway, fine. That's a good point. So
the question still is, so it
would be אסורין Asurin if it's from the יחמור.
Yachmur. No, because if it's coming from having torn off testicles, then
it's אבר מן החי. Ever Min Ha-Chai. Okay, but thank you. All
right. My mistake. We're talking about all kosher animals. Nevertheless, question is
what are these stones? Okay. And according to one scenario, they're ripped
off from a live animal and not kosher. Let's just finish to
the Mishnah. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, שילייא כנגד פניו של
חמור מותר. Shilya Keneged Panav Shel Chamor Mutar. If the, if an...
when the animal was born, the placenta that is opposite the face
of the donkey, that is permissible. Now that's a question. Why isn't
that a product of a non-kosher animal, the placenta? מאי טעמא? Mai
Ta'ama? פירשא בעלמא הוא. Pirsha Be-Alma Hu. It's only waste, refuse. Now
that's true. Why not say the same about urine? Yeah. Okay. So
here's another interesting thing. Even if it's produced by the animal, somehow
if it's considered to be just like gook or whatever, junk, maybe
it doesn't have any status. Like the Gemara said before, if nobody
drinks the urine. But it's a little unclear what it needs to
be considered פירשא. Pirsha. Anyway, let's just finish the Gemara. אמר ליה
רב חסדא, Amar Lei Rav Chisda, תניא דמסייע לך. Tanya De-Mesaye'a Lach.
We have a supporting Baraita. שילייא כנגד פניו של אדם בין חי
בין מת טהור. Shilya Keneged Panav Shel Adam Bein Chai Bein Met
Tahor. The placenta of a human baby, whether the mother, whether there,
whether alive or dead, the mother or the child, is... the placenta
is not... does not have the tumah of dead. So מאי לאו,
Mai Lav, does it not mean
בין הוא חי ואמו חיה, בין הוא מת ואמו מתה, Bein Hu
Chai Ve-Imo Chaya Bein Hu Met Ve-Imo Meta, or even if both
he and the mother are dead? So if he and the mother
are dead, how is the placenta not a part of a dead
body? It must be that we don't consider it to be part
of the mother or part of the child. It's not considered to
actually be a part of the body at all, just some type
of refuse. So, so therefore that supports your idea. Gemara says לא,
Lo, no, that's not necessarily how you read it. Maybe it means
בין הוא חי ואמו מתה בין הוא מת ואמו חיה, Bein Hu
Chai Ve-Imo Meta Bein Hu Met Ve-Imo Chaya, whether the mother is
alive or dead, it doesn't matter, because the placenta maybe is considered
part of the baby. And therefore...
I'm sorry, did I misread it? No, no, the opposite way. בין
הוא חי ואמו... Bein Hu Chai Ve-Imo... Rashi's girsa is... Rashi's girsa
is... where's Rashi's girsa? בין הוא חי ואמו חיה בין הוא מת
ואמו חיה. Bein Hu Chai Ve-Imo Chaya Bein Hu Met Ve-Imo Chaya.
Okay, Rashi switches the girsa. It doesn't matter whether he is alive
or dead, it matters as long as the mother is alive. And
that this placenta is considered to be, the way Rashi has the
girsa of the Gemara, part of the mother. Okay.
So it's a טומאה וטהרה Tumah Ve-Tahara for Tumah and Tahara purposes.
Okay. So the Gemara says והתניא, Ve-Hatanya, one minute, did we not
teach in a Baraita, בין הוא חי ואמו חיה Bein Hu Chai
Ve-Imo Chaya, בין הוא מת ואמו מתה, Bein Hu Met Ve-Imo Meta,
that even if he and the mother are dead, the placenta is
not טמא, Tamei, and that means that it's not considered part of
him or the mother? So the answer is אי תניא תניא. Ei
Tanya Tanya. All right. If you got a Baraita, you got a
Baraita. Then I can't argue. Then you have the evidence. So it
does end interestingly, ignoring that whole question about the stones from the
יחמורתא, Yachmorta, with that final question of how do you define produced?
Why is honey kosher? Is it a special exception or it's not
considered produced? And to produce is defined in more narrow terms. And
that would also be... allow you to be lenient by urine. And
then we have the case about the placenta where it comes up
with this new thing, which is not a question of how did
it get produced, but if it's considered just a refuse, then it's
not considered also part of the animal, which goes back and raises
the question of why wouldn't we say the same by the urine,
but that is another, yet another category that needs defining. Okay, we'll
pick up with the Mishnah tomorrow.
Rabbi, thank you so much for joining us.